Finding Aid of the Society of American Archivists Records, 1935-2016
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Society of American Archivists Records, 1935-2016
Society of American Archivists
UWM Manuscript Collection 172
Accession 2010-018
Accession 2014-035
Accession 2015-024
Accession 2015-038
Accession 2015-015
271.9 cubic ft. (385 boxes, including 16 audio cassettes and 33 videocassettes) 1 oversize folder 8,182 digital files (26.3 GB) 1 film reel 5 microfilm reels approximately 170 books and serial titles plus additions of 2.1 cubic feet (5 boxes and 1 folder)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
The Society of American Archivists (SAA) is the oldest and largest national professional association of archivists in North America. The collection contains materials from the organization of the SAA in 1936 to present day. The main record groups document the activities of the SAA officers; councilors; executive directors; the editorship of The American Archivist; and SAA committees, roundtables, sections, and task forces.
The 1930s saw an unprecedented amount of archival activity in the United States: the establishment of the National Archives (1934); the organization of the Historical Records Survey and the Survey of Federal Archives (1936-1937); and the establishment of the Society of American Archivists (1936), the first professional organization of archivists in North America.
At the December 1935 meeting of the American Historical Association (AHA), a conference of fifty-one participants met to discuss the possibility of forming a national professional organization of archivists. Conference attendees unanimously agreed to establish such an organization at the next AHA meeting and charged a steering committee to draft a constitution. The "Committee of Ten on the Organization of Archivists" was chaired by Solon J. Buck and included Ruth Blair, Theodore C. Blegen, Alexander C. Flick, Curtis W. Garrison, R.B. Haselden, Waldo G. Leland, A.R. Newsome, Margaret Cross Norton, and James A. Robertson.
Attendees of the December 1936 AHA meeting, held in Providence, Rhode Island, approved the draft constitution, and elected officers and a five-member Council. Newsome served as SAA's first president, Norton as vice president, Philip C. Brooks as secretary, and Julian P. Boyd as treasurer. Council members included Blair, Blegen, Buck, Victor H. Paltsists, and Lawrence C. Wroth. The constitution provided for the establishment of twelve committees on a wide variety of topics, including international archival affairs, maps and charts, membership, public relations, reduction of archival material, and terminology. The number of committees was more than the active membership could sustain, and many were inactive for a number of years or eventually allowed to lapse. At this time, the constitution restricted membership to "those who are or have been engaged in the custody or administration of archives or historical manuscripts or who, because of a special experience or other qualifications, are recognized as competent in archival economy." A pro forma election of every applicant for membership was also required.
The first annual meeting was held in Washington, D.C. in June 1937. By this time, 226 individuals had been elected to the Society, one third of whom were women. SAA was largely an east coast organization, with a great number of its leaders coming from the National Archives. It was incorporated in Washington, D.C. in 1945.
SAA's first publication was a 104-page volume of the proceedings of the 1936 organizing meeting and the 1937 annual meeting. The first issue of The American Archivist followed in January 1938. Under the editorship of Theodore C. Pease, professor of history at the University of Chicago, the journal focused more on the use of archives in writing history than on archival administration. This emphasis upset members who felt that The American Archivist should be a trade publication, not a scholarly journal. Tensions over this and other matters led to Pease's resignation in 1945 and the appointment of Margaret Cross Norton, state archivist of Illinois.
During WWII, SAA concentrated on issues relating to the preservation of records not only for historians, but also for the war effort. Several committees reflected these new interests. They included the Collection and Preservation of Materials for the History of Emergencies Committee, the History and Organization of Governmental Emergency Agencies Committee, the Emergency Transfer and Storage of Archives Committee, and the Protection of Archives Against the Hazards of War Committee. At the end of the war, SAA supported the formation of the International Council on Archives (ICA) as a means of rebuilding ties among archivists around the world.
In order to legitimize itself as the national association of archivists, SAA forged relations with other national organizations to discuss issues of mutual concern. A joint committee with the American Association for State and Local History (AASLH) on historical manuscripts eventually led to the National Union Catalog of Manuscript Collections. Meetings with the National Association of State Librarians later led to the formation of the Joint ALA-SAA Committee on Library-Archives Relationships. SAA's status as a national organization was signaled in other ways, as well. In 1947, the annual meeting was held west of the Mississippi for the first time, in Glenwood Springs and Denver, Colorado.
By 1957, membership grew to 648 individual members (as separate from institutional members or subscribers). It reflected an increasingly diverse geographical distribution, with a greater number of members coming from regions other than the east coast. To encourage membership growth, Council passed an amendment in 1955 to accept individuals who are or have been "engaged in the custody, study, teaching, or control of records, archives, or private papers," and those "who wish to support the objectives of the Society." The requirement of a pro forma election of every applicant was also discontinued.
During the mid-1950s, SAA took steps to honor members who made significant contributions to the theory and practice of archival administration, and who thereby encouraged others to improve the standards of the profession. In 1956, the Professional Standards and Training Committee recommended that Council establish "a special class of members of the Society known as Fellows of the Society of American Archivists." A constitutional amendment to that effect was approved at the 1957 annual meeting.
SAA honors the contributions of individuals and archival agencies in other ways. In 1963, the State and Local Records Committee recommended the establishment of the Distinguished Service Award to recognize a North American archival institution, organization, education program, or nonprofit or governmental organization that has given outstanding service to its public and has made an exemplary contribution to the archival profession. Other awards have included the Gondos Memorial Award; the Waldo Gifford Leland Prize; and the Philip M. Hamer Award.
Committees played an important role in advancing SAA's mission, but by the late 1960s it was apparent that various factors hobbled the efforts of committees to communicate and work effectively. Committee members were scattered across the country, conducted most of their work by correspondence and telephone, and usually met only at annual meetings. In his 1968-1969 report on the committee system, Secretary Gerald F. Ham explained that many committees had vaguely defined areas of responsibility or no longer met the needs of the membership. In an attempt to remedy the situation, Council approved a revised structure of standing and ad hoc committees at the December 1969 meeting. In this major reorganization, several committees were abolished, others were consolidated, and the functions and responsibilities of still others were broadened. Additionally, new committees on machine-readable records; oral history; urban and industrial archives; and reference, access, and photo-duplication policies were created. These changes made the committee structure more responsive to the needs of the membership, but they did not help committees work more effectively. The problem of ineffective and inactive committees would be addressed in different ways in the following years.
In 1970, President Philip P. Mason appointed the Committee for the 1970s to "analyze the present structure of the Society, its program and objectives, its relationship with other professional organizations, and most importantly, its needs during the coming decade." Recommendations made by the committee had a decisive impact on the future direction of SAA. The committee focused on eight areas: SAA's organizational structure and operations; relations with other professional groups and organizations; the committee system; SAA publications; membership relations and development; education and training; annual meetings, conferences, and symposia; and finances. An interim report of the committee was distributed to the membership in September 1971, and the final report published in the April 1972 issue of the American Archivist.
Following the recommendation of the Committee for the 1970s, the membership approved an amendment that allowed the elected secretary to be replaced by an executive director. Secretary Robert M. Warner had already served a year of his term when he agreed in 1972 to serve an additional year as the appointed (but unpaid) executive director. In 1973, Warner resigned, and Judith A. Koucky served as acting secretary until a replacement could be found. Ann Morgan Campbell was hired in July 1974 as the first paid executive director, and offices were established on the Chicago Circle campus of the University of Illinois.
Following other recommendations of the Committee for the 1970s, SAA began publication of the SAA Newsletter in 1973 (renamed Archival Outlook in 1993), and established an executive committee to operate for Council between meetings.
In October 1978, Council made another effort to remedy the problem of inefficient and inactive committees. Acting on the recommendation of the Committee on Committees, Council adopted a three-part organization of committees, task forces, and professional affinity groups (PAGs). Standing and joint committees were assigned the function of ensuring the regular conduct of SAA's affairs or representing SAA on inter-association committees with affiliated professions. Task forces were created to address specific issues or questions facing SAA. PAGs were established on the basis of institutional affiliation and/or functional responsibility, and provided members with an opportunity to meet and work with others of similar backgrounds and professional interests. PAGs convened for the first time at the September 1979 annual meeting. All PAGs became known as sections at the end of the annual business meeting in 1983. A fourth unit of SAA, roundtables, was added in January 1985. Like sections, roundtables provided members with similar professional interests the opportunity to meet and work together. Unlike sections, they required a minimum of only twenty members.
Scope and content notes of subgroups are given in the contents list.
Acronyms Used in This Finding Aid
Acronym Expansion
AAM
American Association of Museums
AASLH
American Association for State and Local History
ACA
Association of Canadian Archivists
AHA
American Historical Association
AIA
American Institute of Architects
ALA
American Library Association
AREA
Association of Records Executors and Administrators
ARMA
Association of Records Managers and Administrators
HSS
History of Sciences Society
ICA
International Council on Archives
MARC
Machine-Readable Cataloging
NAGARA
National Association of Government Archives and Records Administrators
NARA
National Archives and Records Administration
NARS
National Archives and Records Service
NEH
National Endowment for the Humanities
NHPRC
National Historical Records and Publications Commission
NMA
National Microfilm Association
OAH
Organization of American Historians
OCLC
Online Computer Library Center
OHA
Oral History Association
PAG, -s
Professional Affinity Group, -s
RLIN
Research Libraries Information Network
SHOT
Society for the History of Technology
UNESCO
United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization
This collection was received in, and is organized in, multiple parts. Additional materials have not been physically or intellectually arranged and interfiled, and researchers may need to consult more than one part of the collection to locate similar materials.
UWM Manuscript Collection 172: Records, 1935-2014
While on deposit at the University of Wisconsin-Madison, the collection was assigned the record group number 200. When it was donated to the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, the collection was assigned a new number (UWM Manuscript Collection 172), but the original record group number was retained on boxes and folders and remains important for paging materials.
President, 1935-2012
Dolores C. Renze, 1959-1967
Albert R. Newsome, 1935-1938
Philip C. Brooks, 1949-1951
Morris L. Radoff, 1954-1955
Everett O. Alldredge, 1963-1964
Herbert E. Angel, 1966-1967
Clifford J. Shipton, 1967-1969
Houston G. Jones, 1968-1969
W. Kaye Lamb, 1964-1965
Wilfred I. Smith, 1972-1977
F. Gerald Ham, 1973-1974
Walter Rundell, Jr., 1977-1978
Elizabeth Hamer Kegan, 1962-1977
Robert H. Bahmer, 1961-1962
Ernst Posner, 1955-1956
Lester J. Cappon, 1951-1957
J. Frank Cook, 1981-1984
Leon deValinger, 1962-1963
Charles E. Lee, 1971-1972
Edward Weldon, 1980-1983
Frank B. Evans, 1986-1989
John A. Fleckner, 1988-1990/
Trudy H. Peterson, 1990-1991
Anne R. Kenney, 1990-1993
Nicholas C. Burckel, 1995-1997
Edie Hedlin, 1993-1994
Timothy Ericson, 2003-2004
Gregor Trinkaus-Randall, 2011-2012
Vice President, 1960-1983
Dolores C. Renze, 1964-1965
W. Kaye Lamb, 1963-1964
Wilfred I. Smith, 1970-1972
F. Gerald Ham, 1972-1973
Walter Rundell, Jr., 1976-1977
Elizabeth Hamer Kegan, 1974-1975
Robert H. Bahmer, 1960-1961
J. Frank Cook, 1981-1983
Secretary, 1936-1976
Correspondence and Subject Files, 1936-1956
Committee Files, 1936-1962
Dolores C. Renze, 1941-1972
Reading File (Outgoing Correspondence), 1956-1964
Committee Files, 1955-1966
General Files, 1941-1972
Council and Officers Files, 1956-1964
Philip C. Mason, 1963-1969
Committee Files, 1963-1968
General Files, 1963-1969
F. Gerald Ham, 1965-1976
Committee Files, 1968-1971
General Files, 1965-1976
Robert M. Warner, 1971-1972
Committee Files, 1971-1972,
General Files, 1971-1972
Treasurer, 1937-1997
Correspondence and Subject Files, 1937-1956
Leon deValinger, 1951-1962
Houston G. Jones, 1961-1968
Almer K. Johnson, Jr., 1967-1972
Howard L. Applegate, 1972-1976
Paul H. McCarthy, 1978-1986
William H. Maher, 1988-1996
Leon Stout, 1994-1997
Council Records and Member Files, 1935-1992
Small Collections, 1935-1981
J. Frank Cook, 1974-1978
Edward Weldon, 1975-1979
Frank Burke, 1976-1980
Edmund Berkeley, Jr., 1977-1981
Susan Holbert, 1981-1985
Trudy Huskamp Peterson, 1984-1987
Anne R. Kenney, 1985-1988
Linda Edgerly, 1987-1989
Richard J. Cox, 1987-1990
James O'Toole, 1988-1992
Executive Director, 1959-2005
Robert M. Warner, 1969-1973
Committee Files, 1972-1973
General Files, 1969-1973
Judith A. Koucky (Acting Secretary), 1970-1974
Committee Files, 1973-1974
General Files, 1970-1974
Ann Morgan Campbell, 1959-1988
General Correspondence, 1974-1986
Council and Officers Files, 1974-1986
Committee Files, 1974-1986
General Files, 1959-1988
Annual Meetings, 1974-1986
Donn C. Neal, 1982-1988
General Correspondence, 1987
Council and Officers Files, 1986-1987
Committee Files, 1986-1987
General Files, 1982-1988
Administrative Files, 1960-2005
Grants, 1979-1997
Subject Files, 1973-2002
Program Officers, 1960-1990
Annual Meetings, 2004-2005
General Correspondence, 1985-1995
Executive Committee Correspondence, 1986-1994
Council Files, 1987-2003
SAA Units Files, 1975-2004
Boards, 1987-2002
Committees, 1975-2002
Representatives, 1985-2002
Roundtables, 1985-2002
Sections, 1986-2004
Task Forces, 1981-2002
American Archivist, 1936-2012
1. Theodore C. Pease, 1936-1946
2. Margaret C. Norton, 1945-1949
3. Karl L. Trever, 1948-1959
4. Philip Bauer, 1955-1959
5. Kenneth Munden, 1959-1965
6. Book Review Editors, 1942-1984
7. Advertising Editors, 1948-1973
8. Kenneth Munden and Harold T. Pinkett, 1928-1972
General Correspondence File, 1946-1971
General Subject File, 1957-1971
Posner Festschrift, 1928-1972
Session Papers, 1967-1970
9. Edward Weldon, 1948-1975
10. Fred Coker, 1959-1978
11. Virginia C. Purdy, 1968-1981
13. Special Issue Editors, 1982
14. Charles R. Schultz, 1982-1983
15. Administrative Files, 1984-2012
18. Correspondence, 1981-1995
Units, 1944-2013
Committees, 1944-2013
Task Forces, 1964-2001
Sections, 1971-2012
Roundtables, 1984-2008
Other Groups, 1971-1997
Annual Meeting Files, Audio-Visual Formats, and Publications, 1937-2014
Annual Meetings, 1937-2004
Photographs, 1937-2014
Sound Recordings, 1988-2012
Annual Meetings, 1988-2012
Microforms and Films, 1938-1966
Publications, 1938-[ongoing]
Realia, 1986, 2000-2011
Education Office, 1979-1994
Basic Archival Conservation Program, 1979-1989
Native American Archives Project, 1980-1986
Preservation Management Training Program, 1984-1994
Education Officer Files, 1982-1989
Members of the Society, 1938-1984
Small Collections
Frank B. Evans, 1964-1975
Ernst Posner, Study of State Archival Programs and Publication of American State Archives, 1940-1966
Leon deValinger, Jr., 1939-1966
Eleanor McKay, 1971-1982
William D. McCain, 1938-1952
J. Frank Cook, 1966-1984
William Moss, SAA China Tour, 1981-1986
SAA Foundation, 2012-2014
The collection contains the following additional accessions.
Accession 2010-018: Additions, 2001-2006
Accession 2014-035: President Edie Hedlin Additions, 1993-1994
Accession 2015-024: Manuscript Repositories Section Additions, 2009, undated
Accession 2015-038: Archival Security Additions, circa 1976-1977
A spreadsheet with file-level information on the electronic records in series 1.27, 8.1, 8.3, 8.4, 9.1, 9.2, and 9.3 is available in the Archives department. These spreadsheets are organized by accession, and some crosswalking may be necessary to find metadata for particular files. Additional technical metadata is available; see an archivist for details.
As of January 25, 2017, all electronic files were accessible on an Intel Core i5-4570 CPU (3.20 GHz, 4 GB RAM) running Windows 7 Enterprise with service pack 1. Software used to access the files includes Windows Picture and Fax Viewer, Adobe Reader, Windows Notepad, LibreOffice, and Windows Media Player.
The collection includes records in the following file formats:
MPEG 1/2 Audio Layer 3 [.mp3]
Graphic Interchange Format 89a [.gif]
Hypertext Markup Language [.html]
Portable Document Format [.pdf]
Rich Text Format [.rtf]
Microsoft Word for Windows [.docx]
Microsoft Word 97-2003 [.doc]
QuickTime for Windows [.mov]
Microsoft Excel 97-2003 [.xls]
Windows Media Video [.wmv]
Acrobat Portable Document Format 1.4 [.pdf]
Tagged Image File Format [.tif]
JPEG File Interchange Format [.jpg]
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
Academy of Certified Archivists Records UWM Manuscript Collection 319
Helen Willa Samuels Papers UWM Manuscript Collection 255
Midwest Archives Conference Records UWM Manuscript Collection 194
Stephen L. Hensen Papers UWM Manuscript Collection 298
Timothy L. Ericson Papers UWM Manuscript Collection 251
Administrative/Restriction Information
Electronic records must be accessed in the Archives reading room, and researchers must use access copies. See an archivist for more information.
Other access restrictions are described in the contents list. Unless noted otherwise, there are no access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
Provision for long-term preservation of SAA's records was originally made by section 21 of its constitution (1936), which reads:
The minute books, correspondence, and other records of the Society and its committees shall be preserved by the officers and chairmen of the committees and shall be promptly turned over by them to the secretary when their terms expire. Records that have ceased to be of use in conducting the current affairs of the Society may, by direction of the council, be turned over to a depository selected by it for permanent preservation.
Until Council designated a depository in the 1960s, the records migrated with each new secretary, who was expected to maintain control over them. This arrangement was manageable when the records amounted to only a few feet, but it proved impractical as their bulk increased. Complicating the situation was the fact that officers and committee chairs were slow in turning over non-active records. When records were passed to the secretary, they often lacked any order. In his report at the annual meeting, Secretary Henry Browne remarked the "exciting arrival" of several boxes from his predecessor, archivist at the Ford Motor Company. The boxes "looked like a do-it-yourself kit for maintaining a Thunderbird," he joked. "They proved to be the archives of the Society."
Dolores Renze, Colorado State Archivist, was the first secretary to make preservation and processing of the records an ongoing priority. During her term, the archives grew substantially. However, like Browne before her, Renze complained that many past presidents and committee chairs declined to turn over their files, and those who did were "most dilatory in applying [to their own records] the principles of preservation and arrangement which they propound" as professional archivists.
On October 2, 1963, Council resolved that "the archives of the Society be deposited in the official custody of an appointed archivist" and that they "be processed, housed, and serviced in conformance with sound archival principles." Upon completing her term as secretary, Renze was appointed as the first SAA archivist, and the Colorado State Archives designated as the official depository.
On December 30, 1969, Council determined that it was again desirable to place the records under the care of the secretary. Accordingly, President Kahn informed Renze that the records were to be placed in the custody of Gerald F. Ham and placed on deposit at the State Historical Society of Wisconsin (now Wisconsin Historical Society) in Madison. Almost two years later, Ham reported that the records had yet to be sent, and Council made arrangements to assist Renze in delivering the records.
During a January 1976 Council meeting, it was reported that the "greatest volume of the Society's archives" were on deposit at the State Historical Society of Wisconsin, although "there were additional segments of the records in the custody of several former SAA officers." Councilor J. Frank Cook chaired a committee to collect records of SAA's first forty years, but it yielded few results. During this time, Council began emphasizing the importance of designating a permanent depository, believing that such action would encourage officers and chairs to transfer inactive records.
On October 2, 1978, Council accepted the offer of the University of Wisconsin-Madison, Division of Archives, to serve as the permanent depository of SAA's archives and appointed Cook as SAA archivist. Cook and the UW-Madison staff provided access to and preserved the records until Cook's retirement in September 2000. At that time, Council donated its archives to the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee (UWM) Libraries and named the head of its Archives Department as SAA archivist. The records arrived at Milwaukee in April 2001. Section 7 of the SAA Constitution currently provides for the placement and preservation of the SAA archives.